Guide to the Intercollegiate Athletics Basketball video 2001-2015
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Intercollegiate Athletics Basketball video
2001-2015
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 368
1.5 linear feet of shelf space 1 box
Video of Washington State University men’s basketball games, mostly from the 2004-2008 season.
Basketball has been an intercollegiate athletic event at Washington State University since early in the 20th century. Games have been filmed on a regular, but not comprehensive, basis since about 1960.
The collection consists primarily of game films of Washington State University men’s basketball, with a small of amount of non-game materials which are mostly promotional in nature. The majority of the game films take place between 2004 and 2008, with a few outliers. There are 59 VHS tapes, and 41 DVDs.
Where information about the source of the materials is given it is noted parenthetically. These include “TV,” presumably the televised broadcast; “truck” which would be the televised broadcast without commercials; and “from XXX” which are materials received from the school WSU was playing against. Some are labeled “offense, “defense,” or “offense/defense” – these were presumably coaching films, cut up and reordered to show only, for example, WSU’s defensive play. A few other parenthetical notes are included; all of these parenthetical notes, as well as all information about the contents, are taken from the labels, not from watching the actual videos. It is possible some videos are mislabeled.
The material is in two format-based series, with VHS tapes preceding DVDs. Within each series are two subseries, with game film (the majority within each series), followed by non-game materials. Materials are ordered chronologically within all subseries.
This collection is open and available for research use.
Materials were donated to the Washington State University Libraries’ Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections on June 19th, 2017 by Debbie Heston of WSU Athletics. They were retained as UA2017-05, and processed in June 2017 by University Archivist Mark O’English.
Other WSU men’s basketball film and video can be found in Archives 195 (1970s miscellany, no games), Archives 211 (1941-1986), Archives 332 (Coach’s shows, 1980s-1996, no games), and Archives 344 (1999-2006).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State University. Sports.; Washington State University. Department of Intercollegiate Athletics.
College sports -- Washington (State)
Colleges and Universities.; Sports and Recreation.; Moving Images.
- Series 1: VHS Tapes
  - Subseries 1.1: Game films
    - Virginia Military Institute (defense only), 2003-11-20 (Box 1, Item 1)
    - Alaska Fairbanks (offense only), 2003-11-22 (Item 2)
    - Montana, 2004-12-13 (Item 3)
    - Idaho, 2004-12-20 (Item 4)
    - Fresno State, 2004-12-22 (Item 5)
    - Gonzaga (truck), 2004-12-28 (Item 6)
    - California (TV), 2004-1-4 (Item 7)
    - Oregon State (TV), 2004-1-15 (Item 8)
    - Oregon (from Oregon), 2004-1-17 (Item 9)
    - Oregon (TV), 2004-1-17 (Item 10)
    - UCLA, 2004-2-5 (Item 11)
    - UCLA (from UCLA), 2004-2-5 (Item 12)
    - USC (truck), 2004-2-7 (Item 13)
    - Washington, 2004-2-19 (Item 14)
    - Arizona State (defense only), 2004-2-26 (Item 15)
    - Arizona State (offense only), 2004-2-26 (Item 16)
    - Arizona, 2004-2-28 (Item 17)
    - Stanford (Pac-10 tournament, TV), 2004-3-11 (Item 18)
    - Lewis-Clark State, 2004-11-10 (Item 19)
    - Georgia Southern (defense/offense), 2004-11-24 (Item 20)
    - Kansas State, 2004-11-27 (Item 21)
    - Idaho, 2004-11-30 (Item 22)
    - Oklahoma State, 2004-12-4 (Item 23)
    - Gonzaga, 2004-12-7 (Item 24)
    - Brigham Young, 2004-12-11 (Item 25)
    - Portland, 2004-12-18 (Item 26)
    - Wyoming, 2004-12-22 (Item 27)
    - UCLA (defense/offense), 2005-1-6 (Item 28)
    - USC, 2005-1-8 (Item 29)
    - Washington (offense/defense), 2005-1-23 (Item 30)
    - Arizona State, 2005-1-27 (Item 31)
    - Arizona, 2005-1-29 (Item 32)
    - Oregon State, 2005-2-10 (Item 33)
    - Oregon, 2005-2-12 (Item 34)
    - Washington, 2005-3-3 (Item 35)
    - Stanford, 2005-3-3 (Item 36)
    - California, 2005-3-5 (Item 37)
    - Stanford (Pac-10 tournament, defense/offense), 2005-3-10 (Item 38)
    - Gonzaga, 2005-12-8 (Item 39)
    - Utah (truck), 2005-12-22 (Item 40)
    - Washington (from UW), 2006-1-7 (Item 41)
    - UCLA (defense/offense), 2006-1-12 (Item 42)
    - USC, 2006-1-14 (Item 43)
    - Stanford, 2006-1-26 (Item 44)
    - California (TV), 2006-1-28 (Item 45)
    - California (from Cal), 2006-1-28 (Item 46)
    - Oregon State, 2006-2-16 (Item 47)
    - Oregon (truck), 2006-2-18 (Item 48)
    - Arizona, 2006-3-2 (Box 2, Item 49)
    - Arizona State (truck), 2006-3-4 (Item 50)
    - Arizona State (from ASU), 2006-3-4 (Item 51)
    - Oregon (Pac-10 tournament), 2006-3-8 (Item 52)
    - Arizona, 2007-2-1 (Item 53)
    - Arizona State, 2007-2-3 (Item 54)
  - Subseries 1.2: non-game materials
    - Commercials, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Item 55)
    - FSN 2005 Preview (Item 56)
    - Selection Sunday (KHQ), 2007-11-03 (Item 57)
    - Klay [Thompson] shooting, 2009-09-02 (Item 58)
    - WSU Scoring Guards - "Recruit to Shoot," undated (Item 59)
- Series 2: DVDs
  - Subseries 2.1: Game films
    - Oregon (from UO), 2004-1-17 (Box 2, Item 60)
    - San Diego State, 2005-12-10 (Item 61)
    - Washington (TV), 2006-1-7 (Item 62)
    - Boise State, 2006-11-25 (Item 63)
    - USC (2nd half only), 2007-3-3 (Item 64)
    - Lewis-Clark State (exhibition), 2007-11-4 (Item 65)
    - Eastern Washington, 2007-11-9 (Item 66)
    - Boise State, 2007-11-13 (Item 67)
    - Idaho, 2007-11-16 (Item 68)
    - Montana, 2007-11-23 (Item 69)
    - Mississippi Valley, 2007-11-24 (Item 70)
    - Air Force, 2007-11-25 (Item 71)
    - Baylor, 2007-11-30 (Item 72)
    - Gonzaga, 2007-12-5 (Item 73)
    - Portland State, 2007-12-9 (Item 74)
    - Citadel, 2007-12-20 (Item 75)
    - North Carolina A&T, 2007-12-28 (Item 76)
    - Washington, 2008-1-5 (Item 77)
    - UCLA (from UCLA), 2008-1-12 (Item 78)
    - Oregon State, 2008-1-17 (Item 79)
    - Oregon, 2008-1-20 (Item 80)
    - Arizona (from UA), 2008-1-24 (Item 81)
    - Arizona, 2008-1-24 (Item 82)
    - Arizona State, 2008-1-26 (Item 83)
    - California, 2008-1-31 (Item 84)
    - Stanford, 2008-2-2 (Item 85)
    - UCLA, 2008-2-7 (Item 86)
    - USC, 2008-2-9 (Item 87)
    - Oregon State (TV), 2008-2-14 (Item 88)
    - Oregon (TV), 2008-2-16 (Item 89)
    - Arizona State, 2008-2-21 (Item 90)
    - California, 2008-2-28 (Item 91)
    - California (from Cal, TV), 2008-2-28 (Item 92)
    - Stanford (TV), 2008-3-1 (Item 93)
    - Winthrop (NCAA 1st round, from NCAA), 2008-3-20 (Item 94)
    - Notre Dame (NCAA 2nd round, from NCAA), 2008-3-22 (Item 95)
    - Notre Dame (NCAA 2nd round, TV), 2008-3-22 (Item 96)
    - Stanford, 2015-1-31 (Item 97)
    - Subseries 2.2: non-game materials
    - Selection Sunday highlights, 2006-2007 (Item 98)
    - Tony Bennett, Mariners first pitch, 2006 (Item 99)
    - WSU vs. All-Stars. Summer Tour, 2007 (Item 100)